Guide to the John Paver Papers, 1920-1979 RL.01003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Paver papers
1920-1979, bulk 1938-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paver, John
RL.01003
33.1 Linear Feet
16,105 Items
Online Items
Selected items from this collection have been digitized and are available in: Resource of Outdoor Advertising Descriptions (ROAD) - Duke Digital Collections
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The John Paver Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from Fairleigh Dickinson University in 1996.
Processing of this collection was supported by the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Biographical Note
1900 Jan. 15 Born in Montgomery, Alabama
1918 Oct.-Dec. Student Army Training Corps enlistee at University of California when World War I armistice signed
1924 Graduated from Northwestern University (Evanston, Ill.) with a Bachelor of Science degree
1925 Graduated from Northwestern with a degree in Civil Engineering
1925 Sept.-1927 Apr. Research Engineer at Sunland Sales Corporation
1927 Apr.-1933 Jan. Chief Engineer-Secretary at the Outdoor Advertising Association of America (OAAA)
1933 Jan.-1936 Jan. Erskine Fellow and Research Associate for Miller McClintock at Erskine Bureau for Street Traffic Research at Harvard University
1936 Jan.-1937 Apr. Research Associate for McClintock at Advertising Research Foundation
1937 Apr.-1942 June Engineer and Manager of National Field Service Department at National Outdoor Advertising Bureau (NOAB)
1942 June-1944 June Major-Lieutenant Colonel in US Air Force during World War II
1944 Jul.-1945 Jan. 1 Managing Director of Traffic Audit Bureau (TAB)
1945 Jan. 1 -1962 President and General Manager of NOAB
1950 Featured speaker at the national convention of the British Poster Advertising Association
1958 Speaker again for the British Poster Advertising Association
1962 Retired from NOAB
1963 Guest of honor and speaker at the European Association of Outdoor Advertising in Paris
1972 Died
After retirement, Paver still promoted the establishment of an international organization to make use of poster advertising throughout the world and traveled extensively for this purpose. He worked closely with the British and London Poster Associations and the Outdoor Advertising Federation of Europe. Paver also published "My World War II Experiences" at some point before 1968. Only a few copies were created by printer, Harry Deckoff, of the Tribune Printing Company in New York
Collection Overview
The John Paver Papers span the years 1920 through 1979, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1938 through the year 1971. The collection documents Paver's career in the outdoor advertising industry, especially his years as president of the National Outdoor Advertising Bureau (NOAB), and his work writing a textbook on the outdoor advertising medium. Series include the Biographical Files Series; Writings and Speeches Series; NOAB Files Series; Subject Files Series; Personal Files Series; Miscellaneous Files Series; Photographs, Negatives, and Slides Series; and Oversize Materials. Researchers interested in the following subjects may find this collection especially helpful: management in the advertising industry, more specifically the outdoor advertising industry; the outdoor medium itself; and traffic and advertising. Common formats in the collection include paper files such as correspondence, meeting minutes, writings, memoranda, printed materials; and photographic prints and negatives. The Resource for Outdoor Advertising Descriptions (ROAD) database, which holds searchable information about the images in this and other outdoor advertising collections will be available in early 2003.
Paver was instrumental in the establishment of standards for traffic measurement and, later, standards and the quality of billboards, topics all reflected in each of the collection's series, especially the Writings and Speeches Series, the NOAB Files Series, and the Subject Files Series. He pioneered research determining the relationship between traffic or habitual movement and trade activities. This work culminated in the publication, Traffic and Trade (McGraw-Hill, 1935), co-authored with research associate Dr. Miller McClintock, and in the founding of the industry authority for measuring outdoor advertising circulation, the Traffic Audit Bureau (TAB). His contributions in the area of window display (show windows) advertising, and, more generally, the outdoor medium are significant as well; all are documented within the collection. A large part of his career was spent in service to the National Outdoor Advertising Bureau before and after World War II; he led the organization for about seventeen years and became a prominent figure in the outdoor advertising industry. The papers document well Paver's work on an outdoor advertising textbook through draft copies and research materials. Through this activity, Paver grew to become a respected authority on poster and painted display advertising in the United States, and served as a speaker and consultant in the last years of his life. For more detailed information about Paver's life and career, see the Biographical Note above as well as the Biographical Files Series. All collection series are further described within the container list.
At the end of this finding aid is a list of publications removed from the collection and cataloged separately. Closely related collections in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library include the John Brennan Papers, the John Browning Papers, the Duplex Advertising Co. Records, the H.E. Fisk Collection of War Effort Mobilization Campaigns, the Outdoor Advertising Association of America Records, the Outdoor Advertising Poster Design Collection, the Outdoor Advertising Slide Library, the Garrett Orr Papers, the R.C. Maxwell Company Records, the Howard Scott Papers, and the Strobridge Lithography Company Photographs.
Publications Removed from the John Paver Papers
Most cataloged separately and represented in the online catalog.
1952 Proceedings. Institute Of Traffic Engineers. Twenty-third Annual Meeting.
Action For Outdoor Recreation For America., Washington, D.C.: Citizen's Committee For The Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission Report, 1964.
All Media Evaluation Study., New York: Sponsor Services Inc., c1954.
American Marketing Journal, 2, no. 3 (July 1935).
BBDO Newsletter, (February 1966) 75th Anniversary Edition.
Bulletin [of the] National Council of State Garden Clubs, Inc., 12, no. 3 (1941).
Cass, Samuel, and Raymond DesJardins. Co-ordinated Transportation. Conn.: Eno Foundation for Highway Traffic Control, 1956.
Cook County Board of Commissioners. Moving Vehicle Method Of Estimating Traffic Volumes and Speeds., Chicago: Inland Press Inc., 1956.
Davis, Clarence and Burkett Van Kirk. Some Rights Of Landowners Adjacent To The Interstate Highway System.Reprinted from Nebraska State Bar Journal 11, no. 1 (January 1962).
Economic and Social Effects of Highway Improvements...A Summary.East Lansing, Mich.: Michigan State University Press, 1961.
The Executive: The Digest of Current Literature for Top Management 5, no. 3 (August 1961).
IMSA Signal Magazine 1, no. 1 (November-December 1965).
IOA Outdoor Newsletter [Institute of Outdoor Advertising] 4, no. 3 (March 1969).
------------ 4, no. 4 (April 1969).
------------ 4, no. 5 (May 1969).
The International Advertiser 3, no. 2 (February 1962).
Joint Assembly and Senate Committee on the Scenic Preservation of State Highways. Report.Sacramento: California State Printing Office, 1931.
Journal of the American Institute of Planners 25, no. 2 (May 1959).
Kettering, Charles F. Research and Social Progress. Speech delivered at the Washington Award Banquet, Palmer House,Chicago, Illinois, February 25, 1936.
Library Classification and Sample Bibliography of Traffic Engineering Materials.New Haven, Conn.: Bureau For Street Traffic Research, Yale University, 1940.
A New Way to Buy Painted Outdoor Advertising. Detroit: Painted Outdoor Advertising Association, 1924.
On Target 2, no. 2 (April 1969).
------------ 2, no. 3 (June 1969).
Outdoor Advertiser 14, no. 75 (Sept. 1961).
------------ 14, no. 6 (July 1962).
Outdoor Advertising News 14, no. 1, (April 1960) [Outdoor Advertising Association of Australia].
------------ 14, no.1 (July 1960) [Outdoor Advertising Association of Australia].
Outdoor Advertising News 54, no 11 (Nov. 1963) [Outdoor Advertising Association of America].
------------ 54, no. 11 (Nov. 1963). [Outdoor Advertising Association of America].
------------ 54, no. 12 (Dec. 1963). [Outdoor Advertising Association of America].
------------ 55, no. 9 (Sept. 1964). [Outdoor Advertising Association of America].
------------ 56, no. 10 (Oct. 1965). [Outdoor Advertising Association of America].
The Outdoor Bulletin 6, no. 12 (Dec. 1961).
The Place of Advertising in the Distributive System. Los Angeles: E. J. Murphy.
Proper Locations for Bus Stops: A Recommended Practice. New Haven, Conn.: Institute of Traffic Engineers, 1954.
Public Relations in Outdoor Advertising.Chicago: Outdoor Advertising Association of America, 1928.
Public Roads 30, no. 5 (Dec. 1958). (2 copies)
Recommended Research Program for Institute of Outdoor Advertising.New York: Advertising Research Foundation, Inc., 1967.
A Report on Automation Trends in the Modern Production Market.Cleveland, Ohio: Penton Publications, 1966.
Riksaffischering: Plats-och Adressförteckning.Stockholm: Wennergren-William A.B.
Roadside Protection: A Study of the Problem and a Zoning Legislative Guide.Washington, D.C.: American Automobile Association.
Signs and Outdoor Display Structures.New York: American Standards Association, 1956.
Suffrin, Harry. This Canadian Food Chain Develops Several Shopping Centers.Conn.: Eno Foundation for Highway Traffic Control, 1956.
A Study of Human Response to Visual Environments in Urban Areas.Arthur D. Little, Inc., 1967.
A Study of Techniques to Measure Response to Urban Roadside Environments.Arthur D. Little, Inc.
Summary of a Study by Arthur D. Little, Inc. Measuring Human Response to the Environment of the Urban Roadside. Commissioned by the Outdoor Advertising Association of America, 1967.
Super Markets and Self-Service Stores: A Study of Their Importance in 694 Cities.Outdoor Advertising Inc., c1946.
A Time for Keen Perspective: Papers from the 1961 Region Conventions.American Association of Advertising Agencies, 1962.
Traffic Engineering 28, no. 8 (May 1958).
------------ 28, no. 11 (Aug. 1958).
------------ 31, no. 7 (April 1961).
Traffic Engineering and Control 5, no. 11 (March 1964).
Traffic Quarterly. Bulletin 10, no. 1 (Jan. 1956).
------------ 12, no. 12 (April 1958).
Traffic estimation; Traffic flow; Show windows; Signs and signboards; Commercial art -- United States; Marketing; Billboards -- United States; Commercial art; Posters -- Design; Posters -- United States; Paver-Sills Traficounter; Poster, American -- 20th century -- United States; Advertising layout and typography; Advertising, Outdoor -- Design and construction -- Standards; Advertising, Outdoor -- Europe; Advertising, Outdoor -- Law and legislation -- United States; Advertising -- Management; Advertising -- Posters; Advertising agencies; Advertising executives; Traffic surveys; Advertising, Outdoor -- Posters; Advertising, Outdoor -- United States; Billboards -- Design and construction -- Standards; Billboards -- Europe; Traffic Audit Bureau (New York, N.Y.); United States. Air Force; Paver family; Outdoor Advertising Association of America; Paver, John; National Outdoor Advertising Bureau; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- Biographical Files Series
  Scope and Contents note
  (See also Legal Size Materials)
  The Biographical Files Series ( 1942-1969) includes narratives typed and printed primarily for publication. Paver apparently wrote and rewrote the information in many different forms to suit individual purposes. Some documents include details of his work and military experience ( U.S. Air Force), athletic experience, work performed for NOAB, as well as résumés, and letters of congratulation and recommendation, including items from Miller McClintock, J. Walter Thompson advertising executive Norman Strouse, and others. A publicity file holds articles and other printed materials containing various blurbs about Paver.
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Information (Box 1)
    - 1942-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1942-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
  - NOAB Service, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Publicity, 1927-1965 (Box 1)
- Writings and Speeches Series
  (See also Legal Size and Oversize Materials)
  The Writings and Speeches Series ( 1923-1972) contains a mix of document formats. Much of the correspondence, memoranda, printed materials, and other non-manuscript items are presumed to relate to the drafts with which they are foldered--probably as research materials. The majority of the items in this series are draft pieces of Paver's planned textbook on the outdoor advertising medium, mostly in holograph (handwritten) or typescript formats, although the book was never published. Book segment titles were distinguished or subjects were assigned to folders wherever possible. The series is divided into two subseries, Writings and Speeches by Paver, and Writings and Speeches by Others. Paver's materials are further subdivided into three groups: (1) files created for his textbook, (2) speeches by Paver, and (3) miscellaneous writings by Paver. Writings and Speeches by Others contains far fewer items, but has similar groupings within it. Photographic materials from this series and all others have been removed to the Photographs, Negatives, and Slides Series. Photocopies of most photographs were left in original order to preserve context.
  - Writings and Speeches by Paver Subseries
    - Textbook Files (alphabetical by subject)
      Paver's textbook files are evidence of his efforts to create a comprehensive introduction and analysis of the outdoor medium. Folders with title- or subject-identified materials make up the initial alphabetical run. These are most often typescripts with holograph edits, but there are some holograph manuscripts as well. Included are long descriptions of both subjects and organizations such as "the advertising agency," the Advertising Council, the National Outdoor Advertising Bureau, the Traffic Audit Bureau, the Outdoor Advertising Association of America, the American Association of Advertising Agencies, the Advertising Research Foundation, techniques of buying, art creation, writing advertising copy, market coverage, painted displays, public relations, and more general topics such as " Outdoor Advertising in the US."
      - The Advertising Agency, Typescript with Holograph Edits, 1968 (Box 1)
      - The Advertising Council, Typescript, undated (Box 1)
      - Advertising Research Foundation, Old Chapter XXI, undated (Box 1)
      - "American Association of Advertising Agencies," Typescript, undated (Box 1)
      - Art and Copy, Chapter XII, Typescript, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Association of National Advertisers and NOAB, Typescript, undated (Box 1)
      - Buying Techniques, Chapter VII, Typescript, undated (Box 1)
      - Cooperative Methods, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Creation of Message Technique, Typescript Fragments with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Determination of Allotments, Typescript and Fragments, 1968 (Box 1)
      - Discounts, Miscellaneous Typescript Fragments with Holograph Edits, 1971 and undated (Box 1)
      - Discounts and Pricing, Typescript Fragment, undated (Box 1)
      - Economical Coverage Manuscripts, 1935, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Educational Programs, Typescript with Holograph Edits, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
      - "Effect of Freeways on the Outdoor Medium," Typescript and a Los Angeles Survey, 1965 and undated (Box 1)
      - Evolution of the Medium, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Future of Outdoor Advertising, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Media Selection, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Media Volume Statistics, up to 1965 (Box 1)
      - Merchandising, Typescript Fragments and Sample Ads, undated (Box 1)
      - MONI (Metropolitan Outdoor Network, Inc.) and National Sales, Typescript, 1968 (Box 1)
      - Painted Display, Pricing, Typescript, undated (Box 1)
      - Painted Displays, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Public Relations, Typescript with Holograph Edits, 1963-1972 (Box 1)
      - Public Relations/Criticism, Typescript with Holograph Edits, 1958-1968 (Box 1)
      - Qualities of Outdoor Advertising, 1951-1964 (Box 1)
      - Reach Frequency, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - Traffic Audit Bureau (TAB) Program, 1964-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Traffic Audit Bureau (TAB), Typescript Copies, 1972 and undated (Box 1)
      - Transportation Advertising, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 1)
      - United States, Typescript with Holograph Edits, 1964 (Box 1)
      - Users of Outdoor Advertising, Typescripts, undated (Box 1)
      - Variation of Values, Holograph and Typescript Fragments with Holograph Edits, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Textbook Files (alphabetical by part of book)
      The next alphabetical run within Paver's textbook files contains items comparable to the alphabetical by subject group, but is ordered by genre/book part. It includes portions Paver labeled as the appendix, illustrations, and more. There are traffic flow graphs and a glossary of industry terms helpful for the novice advertiser. In addition, there are outlines, questionnaire results, and a large number of manuscript fragments. Similar to the previous group, these files describe outdoor advertising in detail, but also highlight its importance in the world with fragments such as one titled, "Posters as a Visual Aid in Projecting America's Image to the World." Paver compared the medium to others, wrote about industry changes and outdoor advertising abroad, and discussed industry research.
      - Appendix, undated (Box 2)
      - Forms, 1938-1968 (Box 2)
      - Glossary, Typescript, undated (Box 2)
      - Glossary, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 2)
      - Illustrations, Chapter 1, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Illustrations, Chapter X, 1958 and undated (Box 2)
      - Illustrative Material, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Negatives for Book, Japan, undated (Box 2)
      - Outline for Textbook, undated (Box 2)
      - Outline for Advertising Techniques, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Questionnaire Results, The Medium, 1968 (Box 2)
      - Questionnaire Results, 1968 (Box 2)
      - Typescript Fragments (Miscellaneous):
        - 1933-1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - 1948-1962 and undated (Box 2)
        - 1948-1963 and undated (Box 2)
        - 1949-1958 (Box 2)
        - 1950-1968, 4 folders (Box 2)
        - 1953 and undated (Box 2)
        - 1955 and undated (Box 2)
        - 1960-1964 and undated, 4 folders (Box 2)
        - 1960-1964 and undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - 1960-1969 (Box 3)
        - 1961 and undated (Box 3)
        - 1962 and undated (Box 3)
        - 1962-1965 (Box 3)
        - 1964 (Box 3)
        - 1964 and undated (Box 3)
        - 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - undated, 7 folders (Box 3)
      - Volume II:
        - Table of Contents Typescripts and Additional Fragments, 1960 (Box 3)
        - Typescript Fragments Miscellaneous, 1960 and undated (Box 3)
    - Speeches
      Paver's speeches reveal his broad knowledge of the outdoor advertising industry; he spoke on the medium in general as well as on more specific topics like traffic measurement. This group of materials is evidence of his many speaking engagements in his home state of Texas, as well as abroad for the British Poster Advertising Association and the Outdoor Advertising Association of Australia. Paver also presented to organizations such as state outdoor advertising associations, and to smaller groups including a student women's advertising club. A number of the speeches were obviously connected to his work with the National Outdoor Advertising Bureau or were at least given during his employment there.
      - Ad Club Speech, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 3)
      - Austin Speech, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 3)
      - Australia Speech, Typescript with Holograph Edits, undated (Box 3)
      - Australia Speech, Typescript, 1959 (Box 3)
      - British Poster Advertising Association Speech, 1958 and undated (Box 3)
      - Canada Speech, Typescript, 1959 (Box 4)
      - Houston Speech, Typescript, 1954-1957 (Box 4)
      - International Congress Speech, Typescript, 1960 (Box 4)
      - NOAB Speeches, Typescript, 1962 (Box 4)
      - Pennsylvania Meeting Speech, Typescript, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Poster Advertising Association of Canada Meetings, Typescript With Holograph Edits, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Speeches, Miscellaneous:
        - 1945-1954, 4 folders (Box 4)
        - 1956-1959, 3 folders (Box 4)
        - 1960, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 4)
        - 1961, 5 folders (Box 4)
        - 1962 and undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Writings
      Miscellaneous writings by Paver, some going back to the beginnings of his advertising career, include files regarding his college thesis on transportation in Chicago, and Traffic and Trade Research Report, a work completed at Harvard, 1934. There is a broader picture of the man in drafts of his World War II experiences and family history.
      - Outdoor Advertising in Africa, undated (Box 4)
      - Chicago Subway College Thesis: (Box 4)
        - 1923 and undated (Box 4)
        - 1924 and undated (Box 5)
        - 1924 (Box 5)
        - undated (Box 5)
      - Paver History, Typescript, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Paver History, Typescript, undated (Box 5)
      - Trade Articles, 1958-1961 (Box 5)
      - Traffic and Trade Research Report, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Writings and Speeches by Others Subseries
    Paver likely used these materials in his research and writings on the industry. Authors include advertising executives Norman Strouse and Kerwin Fulton. Topics such as advertising leasing, criticism and other problems facing the industry, advertising and war, NOAB, personnel, and European outdoor advertising are discussed. The files are primarily arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Davidson, Craig, Advertising Agency-Media Relations, 1945 (Box 5)
    - Fulton, Kerwin H. et al, Miscellaneous Writings, 1938-1957 (Box 5)
    - [Henry], Leasing, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Hopkins, Frank T. Speeches, 1936-1940 (Box 5)
    - Resor, Stanley, The Importance of Ideas in Selling, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Speeches, Miscellaneous:
      - 1941-1962 (Box 5)
      - 1945-1949, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 1948-1952 (Box 5)
      - 1952-1958 (Box 5)
      - 1954 (Box 5)
      - 1954-1956 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Excerpts from TAB), 1965-1968 (Box 5)
    - Typescript Fragments [by Cerrini?], 1965 (Box 5)
- National Outdoor Advertising Bureau (NOAB) Files Series